<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Michaels combat with the diuel: or, Moses his funerall Delivered in a sermon preached in St. Pauls Church, on Sunday morning, being the Feast of St. Michael, 1639. By Iohn Blenkovv, LL.B. sometime Fellow of S. Iohn Bap. Coll. in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Blenkow, John, b. 1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115575</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850793</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1090:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Michaels combat with the diuel: or, Moses his funerall Delivered in a sermon preached in St. Pauls Church, on Sunday morning, being the Feast of St. Michael, 1639. By Iohn Blenkovv, LL.B. sometime Fellow of S. Iohn Bap. Coll. in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Blenkow, John, b. 1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>The feast of St. Michael is on Sept. 29.--Folger Shakespeare Library catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Errata at foot of E1v, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MICHAELS COMBAT WITH THE DIVEL: OR, MOSES his FUNERALL. Delivered in a Sermon Preached in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> PAULS Church, on Sunday Morning, being the Feaſt of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Michael,</hi> 1639. By IOHN BLENKOVV, LL. B. ſometime Fellow of S. <hi>Iohn Bap. Coll.</hi> in OXFORD.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bernard. in Epiſt. Dom. 2. Serm.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quantò ſublimitas notior, tantò humilitas pretioſior.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Reſiſt the Divel, and he will flie from thee.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Iam. 4.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16020:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16020:2"/>
            <head>To the Right VVorſhipfull, Sir <hi>HENRY MARTIN</hi> Knight, Iudge of his Majeſties Court of <hi>Admiralty,</hi> and the Prerogative Court of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AY it pleaſe you to take into your hand, that, which not long ſince you receyved into your eare, with undeſerved attention and favourable cenſure: (the which only, next your
<pb facs="tcp:16020:3"/> private favours, encouraged mee to fixe your Name.) And to let it ſhrowde under your Protection, which otherwiſe would bee loath to walke at all abroad. It deſires to baulke the common eye, as too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy an object; onely content to viſit private friends: ſome, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it may find; your Name may make it many: your ſelfe is <hi>inſtar omnium.</hi> If you pleaſe to accept it, as firſt or chiefe, it ſhall embolden the Authour to ſubſcribe himſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The meaneſt of your obliged IOHN BLENKOVV.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16020:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Epiſtle of Saint Iude, verſe 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yet Michael the Archangel, when contending with the Divel, he diſputed about the body of Moſes, durſt not bring a rayling accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt him, but ſayd, The Lord rebuke thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW I have read my Text, let mee call upon you to heare the word of God. For theſe words, eyther through the ignorance or peeviſhneſſe of ſome, were not commonly taken for ſuch. This verſe, with ſome others, in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of ſacred Writ, being generally held Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphall; inſomuch that the whole Epiſtle was called in queſtion, and ſcarcely obtayned to bee accounted within the verge of the Canon. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not without ſome ground: for that this ſtory of <hi>Michael,</hi> and that Prophecy of <hi>Enoch,</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the 14 verſe, are not to be found any where in Scripture. And although Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (out of whom our ſacred Plagiary, Saint <hi>Iude</hi> hath taken
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16020:4"/> moſt of his Epiſtle) have the ſame ſenſe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall termes, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. That the Angels which are greater in power and might, bring not a rayling accuſation, &amp;c. Yet that <hi>Michael</hi> did ever contend with the Divell, and contending did uſe ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, we read not any where recorded, but by our Apoſtle in this place. Some ſay therefore, that this ſtory was a common tradition amongſt the Hebrewes, and from them our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle had it. Others, that it might be ſome Booke then extant, which is ſince periſhed. <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> name one intituled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the Aſcention of <hi>Moſes:</hi> out of which probably it might be taken. And why not ſo, ſince Saint <hi>Paul</hi> before him, quoted <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Menander,</hi> and <hi>Epimenides.</hi> Certayne it is; that many bookes of Scripture are loſt: As the bookes of the Battels of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 21.14. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 10.13,</note> mentioned by <hi>Moſes.</hi> The booke of the Righteous cited by <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> the bookes of <hi>Shemaiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Iddo</hi> the Seer, and <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet: many of the workes of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and much of the Chronicles. Out of one or other of which this ſtory might be inſerted, and receive like authority with thoſe which are of as obſcure antiquity. <hi>Moſes</hi> doth no where report how <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> withſtood him, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. and more then that too: for he ſayth, that our Saviour was ſeene of more then of five hundred brethren at once, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And that <hi>tacentibus Evangeliſtis,</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts ſaying no ſuch thing. Saint <hi>Luke</hi> bids us remember what our Saviour ſometime ſayde,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16020:4"/> 
               <hi>It is better to give then to receive:</hi> but yet makes no quotation for it, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.35. And it is eaſily to be ſuppoſed (ſayth <hi>Iuſtinian</hi>) that the Apoſtle would not uſe a feigned inſtance in ſo ſerious a matter,<note place="margin">In Loc.</note> or not rather an undoubted truth, whereſoever recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. I will not follow the matter ſo hard upon my Author, as ſcrupulouſly to queſtion where he had it, ſince I finde it heere. I conclude with him (and that no meane Author) both modeſtly and confidently: <hi>Vt ut eſt ex Iudâ certum eſt hanc Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam eſſe Canonicam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide in Loc.</note> From whence ſoever it bee taken, it is in <hi>Iude</hi> Canonicall. Truth is truth, where ever found, which diſtild from the pen of the holy Ghoſt, becomes divine verity. A ſtory by tradition, or Apocryphal, may be true, many times is, to which if the ſacred Spirit pleaſe to ſet his hand, and deliver it to us as his act and deede, muſt neceſſarily be authenticall.</p>
            <p>Not to hold you long in a perchance unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Quaere.</hi> The words in generall, are an Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call narration of a certaine contention, occaſional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had betweene <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel, and the Divel, at the funerall of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And they offer themſelves to your conſideration, under theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: Firſt, The contention it ſelfe, <hi>Hee ſtrove againſt the Divell, and diſputed about the body of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> Secondly, His demeanour, or behaviour in this contention, <hi>He durſt not bring a rayling accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt of theſe, obſerve, 1. The perſons ſtriving, <hi>Michael the Archangel, and the Divel.</hi> 2. The matter of their ſtrife, or about what they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16020:5"/> ſtrove, <hi>The body of Moſes.</hi> 3. The maner of their ſtriving, how they ſtrove, and that is by way of diſputation or diſcourſe, <hi>They diſputed.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Generall. His behaviour it ſelfe, <hi>He durſt not &amp;c.</hi> and that is ſet downe, 1. Negatively, <hi>Hee durſt not bring a rayling, &amp;c</hi> 2. Affirmatively, He ſayd, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi> Of which, in order, as God ſhall aſſiſt me, your Chriſtian patience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me, and my weake memory ſuffer me.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the Contention it ſelfe: and therein, firſt of the perſons contending, <hi>Michael &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, of the firſt perſon contending, <hi>Michael the Archangel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This name is one of thoſe ſixe names of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which ſome have reckoned to bee found ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in Scripture. It imports, according to Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie, Power or fortitude. <hi>Michael interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quis ut Deus:</hi> Who is ſo ſtrong as our God? Whether this be the Archangels proper name, or no, may be a queſtion. Since ſome have doubted whether Angels have any proper or particular names whereby to be diſtinguiſht, aſſigned them by God: and have concluded the contrary. viz. that thoſe bleſſed ſpirits have not any proper or peculiar names. The which opinion <hi>Zanchy</hi> hath thought moſt probable, and ſeemes to maintayne. And as for thoſe names which were given them in Scripture, 1. they were given them onely for a time, to be diſtinguiſht by, while they were in employment among men: 2. to denote and imply their office, and meſſage, about which they were ſent: and ſo <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſignifieth, <hi>the fortitude of God:</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16020:5"/> even that <hi>fortitude,</hi> he would have him to exerciſe at this or that preſent time, about this or that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar deſigne. So <hi>Raphael</hi> hath his name from healing or curing diſeaſes, which was the mayne intent of his comming to <hi>Tobit. Tob.</hi> 3.17. And the Angel of the Lord, namely <hi>Raphael,</hi> was ſent to heale them both. So <hi>Michael</hi> ſignifying pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is brought in as a Champion of the Church of God, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. And under that name he defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Elect againſt the Dragon, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.7. And ſo of the reſt. And thus as they are names of office, ſo were they not appropriate or perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall; but eyther continued to them for the ſame purpoſe, or transferred to ſome who ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame office, at the good will &amp; pleaſure of Almighty God. <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim unus tantum Angelus curandis morbis praefectus eſt, ſed alii etiam ad idem faciendum mitti aut ſolent aut poſſunt. Nomen igitur Raphaelis unius Angeli proprium eſſe credendum non eſt: &amp; idem de aliis dicendum eſſe, quis dubitet? Zanch. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de Oper. Dei, c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>And that they have names in Heaven, may ſeeme improbable, in this reſpect, becauſe the ſame reaſon holdeth not. It might bee requiſite, that whileſt they were on Earth, they ſhould have names, in regard of the weake capacity of humane Nature, who cannot otherwiſe or well diſtinguiſh things but by their names; which was the reaſon why <hi>Adam</hi> at the firſt, impoſed names upon all creatures. As likewiſe to confirme the reality of their appearance, which otherwiſe might bee thought fantaſticall, or a meere <hi>deceptio viſus,</hi> or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16020:6"/> to confirme their predictions, by the name of him that foretold them; and ſo the Angel tels <hi>Mary</hi> his name, I am <hi>Gabriel.</hi> And <hi>Manoah</hi> did at leaſt deſire the name of the Angel which appeared to him for that purpoſe. Or rather for ſome reaſon beſt knowne to him that impoſed them. But this reaſon ceaſeth in Heaven, where not onely God himſelfe knoweth every Angel, but every Angel knowes every of his fellows in particular. Beſides, neyther have they any voyce, as being ſpirits, whereby names are to be expreſſed; inaſmuch as all things in Heaven are done after a ſpirituall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by divine revelation, or otherwiſe in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible ſort. Thus farre goeth <hi>Zanchy.</hi> And thus farre I lead the Curious, whom I leave to their leyſure to determine of ſo unneceſſary a <hi>quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> And if any will be further troubleſome, I muſt anſwer him as the Angel did <hi>Manoah, Iudg.</hi> 13.18. about the ſame queſtion; Why askeſt thou thus after their names, ſince they are ſecret? Neyther whether they have or not, can bee knowne: and in the ſilence of the Holy Ghoſt, to determine any thing, may be raſh and unwarrantable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Arcbangel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This name is obſerved to be alwayes given to the better Angel, and is ſtill found in the ſingular number; which hath given occaſion to ſome, to doubt, whether there are more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on Archangel, or no: That there are many or more, may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion. The general &amp; more proper collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hence, is this, that there are orders and degrees in Heaven amongſt thoſe bleſſed and glorious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16020:6"/> an Archangel ſuppoſeth an Angel, and ſo of the reſt. However in this particular, the Schooles may ſeeme to have beene too curious, Who out of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> have added Thrones, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, Vertues, Principalities, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1. Out of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> Cherubims. Out of <hi>Eſay</hi> Seraphims: and this done, take their pen and definitively ſet downe nine orders or degrees. But how they will make them good, thats the Queſtion: for that the deduction is weake and unwarrantable, not able to overſway the contrary opinion of many other Learned, who though they hold ſome kinde of order and ſubordination amongſt the Angels, yet they are not ſo bold as to aſſign in particular their degrees and orders: and to affirme a thing ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from our underſtanding, were neceſſary ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome evident reaſon, or more firme authority then can be alleadged for ſo determinate a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: <hi>Eſſe Sedes, Dominationes, &amp;c.</hi> That there are Thrones, and Dominations, and Principalities, &amp;c. I doe firmely beleeve, ſayth S. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> and that they differ in ſome ſort, but how I know not, nor do I think my ſelfe diſparaged by that ignorance. And for my owne part, when I ſhould have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to occupy my buſines in ſuch great waters as theſe, I would rather deſire to be commended for my neat ſtroake in ſwimming over them, then for my skill in diving into them.</p>
            <p>Well, an Archangell he is, <hi>Vnus de Principibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Rom. Pont l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> S Poſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> a chiefe or principal Angel, as <hi>Vatablus</hi> there, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.13. The great Prince, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affirmes, that <hi>Michael</hi> ever ſince the fall of <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16020:7"/> is Head of the glorious Angels: but he doeth not tell us how he came to be choſen in <hi>Lucifers</hi> room. Others, that he is the tutelar Angel of the Church Catholike, and of the Head thereof, the Pope; with many other offices which they put upon him without warrant, and to little purpoſe. Some more probable then any of theſe, have thought that he was that very ſame Angel, which condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the children of Iſrael over the Red Sea, and in the Wilderneſſe, in their voyage to the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> This I am ſure of, notwithſtanding theſe opinions, he was reputed by <hi>Daniel,</hi> the chiefe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of the Iewes, and the Defender of Gods people; and therein a type of Chriſt, the true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of his Church. And ſo wee may conclude him heere as being now ſet in oppoſition againſt the Divel, in a cauſe tending to the ſame purpoſe. And ſo much of the one party contending, <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> the Archangell. The other is the Divell: <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer,</hi> as, tis ſuppoſed, and ſo the Prince of Divels, to be the Antagoniſt to the Prince of the Angels. However there is <hi>impar congreſſus,</hi> an unequall match, and not likely to prevayle. Hee was once a puiſſant ſpirit, &amp; of redoubted proweſſe, whileſt he ſtood intire; but having caught ſo damnable a fall as he did, hee was never ſince able to recover the ſtrength he then loſt, and obtaine conqueſt in what ever quarrell he did engage himſelfe, as the iſſue of this preſent conflict will proove. I ſhall therefore paſſe over his perſon, with the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his malice and boldneſſe; who, as if not conſcious of his owne weakeneſſe by his fall, dare
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16020:7"/> yet beare up, and affront the Captaine of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Hoſt. His malice will not ſuffer him but to contend, though without hope of victory: ſtrive the will, be it at never ſo great diſadvantage. Our Savior himſelfe muſt not baulke his aſſault, thogh he get nothing by the attempt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. As for Saint <hi>Michael</hi> and he, it ſeemes contention was ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry betweene them; wee ſtill finde them fighting together. <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, againſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell and his Angels, in a ſolemne ſet Battell. And if we will underſtand there, by <hi>Michael,</hi> Chriſt, as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth; <hi>Per Michaelem intellige Chriſtum.</hi> It may confirme the care of our Saviour over his Church, who will never ſuffer it to want a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, though himſelfe go in perſon to the Battell. And by that meanes, the Divel and his forces ſhall ſtill be routed and put to flight: And in this ſtands our comfort, that maugre all his malice, wee ſhall be able to be conquerours, yea more then conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, in him that loveth us, and gave himſelf for us. Roare he may, Lion as he is; faſten he cannot: ſeeke his pray he muſt, if happily hee can ſo finde it, readily fetch it he cannot: wait hee muſt upon God for what he hath; Gods permiſſion is the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels commiſſion: where he pleaſeth to give up his right, there onely the Divell takes poſſeſſion: and of this we are ſure, that he will never fayle thoſe who put themſelves under the ſhadow of his wings. And thus much of the perſons conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Come wee now to the matter of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, in the next words:
<q>The body of Moſes.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16020:8"/>
            <p>There are that hold that <hi>Moſes</hi> never died, and interpret Gods burying of him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.6. of his Tranſlation or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and ſome of the Fathers have made mention of a Booke intituled to that purpoſe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the aſcenſion or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of Moſes into Heaven, as after we reade of <hi>Elijah.</hi> The which they rather beleeve, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſayd both of them to appeare,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.2.</note> and talke with Chriſt in the transfiguration. Others have thought, that though <hi>Moſes</hi> indeed died, yet God did not bury him, but that God appointed him the place of his Sepulchre, and he there made a Cave, into the which he entred and dyed, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of the Lord, and had no other maner or ceremony of interring or inhumation: and ſo it came to paſſe, that no man ever yet knew of his Sepulchre. But it is certaine, that both theſe are falſe: For firſt, that <hi>Moſes</hi> died is evident, So <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the ſervant of the Lord died, Deut.</hi> 34.5. And that being dead, he buried not himſelfe, is likewiſe plain in the words that follow, that <hi>The Lord buried him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 6.</note> And had it not beene ſo, his Sepulchre had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver continued to this day unknowne. Let <hi>Moſes</hi> bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry himſelfe never ſo ſecretly, the Divell would have beene privy to it, (as we ſee he is heere not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding) and no doubt would have eaſily acquainted thoſe with it, whom it might concern for the future. It is certayne enough then, that God buried him: that is, as Interpreters generally agree, by the Miniſtry of the Archangell in the Text, or at leaſt together with ſome other appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that purpoſe, <hi>Michael</hi> yet having the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16020:8"/> hand in the deſigne. And ſurely ſome neede there was: <hi>Moſes</hi> is no ſooner dead, and going to his grave, but the Divel would have arreſted the corps: and hence grew the preſent contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Michael</hi> and him.</p>
            <p>The contents of this ſtrife, hath bred a various conceit amongſt Interpreters, and as it ordinarily falleth out in matters of this nature, one ſayth one thing, another, another. Ten ſeverall opinions are cited by <hi>Lorinus</hi> concerning this matter. I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to cite them. The moſt generall and ſetled determination is: That whereas <hi>Michael</hi> would have buried <hi>Moſes</hi> privately, as God commanded, the Divel would have him buried openly and in publike view. And whereas <hi>Michael</hi> would not have his Sepulchre knowne, the Divel laboured by all meanes to publiſh it. Upon this, <hi>Michael</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts him: the Divel urgeth the contrary, and hence aroſe the ſtrife.</p>
            <p>The Divels intent, as it could not be good, ſo it might eaſily be gheſt: viz. to wit, that thereby he might draw the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Idolatry, which were happily too prone already. Which God knowing, prevented them in This, as a further oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, conveying his body away from them.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie to be conceived, that they who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt the Brazen Serpent, might in time to come, worſhip the ſetter up of it. Neyther could thoſe many ſignes and wonders which he did amongſt them, chuſe but heighten the conceit of a deity, and cauſe them to worſhip him as a God after his death, whom they ſo extraordinarily honoured
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16020:9"/> in his life. Their preſent eſtimation muſt needes be eaſily improoved into future ſuperſtition. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides they had ſometime heard that of God to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 7.1. I have made thee a God to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhalbe thy Prophet. And what comment they might have made upon thoſe words, may probably be imagined. And though a dead body may ſeeme but a cold argument to perſwade divinity, and a ſpectacle of Mortality might well have daſht the conceit of a Deity; Yet conſidering how fooliſh ſuperſtition hath ever beene, <hi>Superſtitio ſemper ſtolida:</hi> Superſtition was ever fooliſh.<note n="*" place="margin">Illos pro diis vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chra habent. Lact.</note> And how feazable a thing it is in it ſelfe; it will not be hard to conceive how the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Moſes</hi> might eaſily have become an Idoll. What were all thoſe numberleſſe Deities, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſo fondly and devoutly worſhipt? Were they not men, famous in their generations, and the glory of their times? as the Wiſeman ſpeaketh, Good Kings, Honourable Parents, Noble Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, Couragious Warriours. And to this <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> &amp; <hi>Lactantius</hi> have aſcribed the firſt original of all Idolatry. viz. the ſuperſtitious having of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s perſons in admiration after their deaths. <hi>Iupiter, Mercury, Saturne, &amp;c.</hi> what were they but men, who for their benefits and deſerts came at the firſt to be accounted for deities. And what? Was <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> behinde any of theſe, yea what were they in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of him? <hi>There aroſe not a Prophet ſince in Iſrael like</hi> Moſes, <hi>whom the Lord knew face to face. In all the ſignes and wonders which the LORD ſent him to doe in the Land of</hi> Aegypt <hi>to</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16020:9"/> to all his ſervants, and to all his land, and in all that mighty hand, and in all the great terrour which</hi> Moſes <hi>ſhewed in the ſight of all Iſrael. Deut. ult. v.</hi> 10. 11. 12. Could all Iſrael know this and not bee rapt with more then an ordinary conceit of his perſon, after his death, whom they welnigh adored in his life. To put this out of queſtion, it was, without doubt, the cauſe why God hid his body. Neither can there bee any reaſon aſſigned why hee ſhould ſo doe, ſaith <hi>Cor. a Lapide,</hi> but leſt the Iews ſhould worſhip him. This the Divel wel knew,<note place="margin">In Loc.</note> and that made him ſo earneſtly contend for his body, only that he might make an Idoll of it.</p>
            <p>And if this may yet be thought incredible, let his dayly practice prove it by experience. What greater ſuperſtition hath hee brought in, in theſe later dayes, then by theſe meanes? What pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; prayers, devotions, have beene given in way of homage to the Shrines of deceaſed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs? What a treaſure of precious reliques hath hee raked out of the duſty graves of departed Saints, with which he beſots the miſled fancyes of theſe dayes? We cannot but ſee to what excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent purpoſe the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> would have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; when we ſee ſo many armes, legges, hands, feet, &amp; fingers of Martyrs, to be had in ſuch reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent if not divine eſtimation. Good reaſon there was therfore, that <hi>Michael</hi> ſhould ſtand up in the defence of it, &amp; vindicate it out of his hands who would ſo have proſtituted it to idolatrous uſes.</p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee what the Divel would have done had he had his will. Yet ſee the diligence of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16020:10"/> cunning deceyver: <hi>Omnem movebit lapidem:</hi> Hee will not leave any ſtone unmooved, to promote his intentions, no not a grave ſtone. The Divel would fayne bee trying experiments on <hi>Moſes</hi> body. The grave ſhall not bee free from his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, if he can prevayle: neyther at leaſt ſhall they be free from <hi>Impuſture,</hi> where realities fayle. If God will not let him touch the dead bodies of his Saints, yet he doth often make uſe of their ſhapes: If the ſubſtance be denied him, the apparition ſhall ſerve turn to deceive. If <hi>Saul</hi> ſtand in need, <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhall come up in the very mantle he uſed to weare in his life time. But let it be our wiſdome to know theſe ſleights, and our Chriſtian courage to reſiſt them. And thus much of the matter about which they contended, <hi>The body of Moſes.</hi> I proceede to the maner, how they contended, and that was by way of diſputation or diſcourſe;
<q>Altercabantur, They diſputed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Touching Angelicall locution (to which this particular of my Text hath reference;) It hath beene an ancient queſtion among the Fathers, and occaſioned by divers places of Holy Writ. The Seraphims ſtood upon it, &amp;c. <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.2.3. And one Cryed to the other, Holy, Holy, Holy, is the Lord God of Hoſts. Out of which that of Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his <hi>Te Deum,</hi> To thee all Angels Cry aloud, &amp;c. To thee Cherubim and Seraphim continually doe cry. So <hi>Zach.</hi> 2. Behold the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel which ſpake in me, went foorth, and another Angel went foorth to meet him, and Sayde unto him. More expreſly in the new Teſtament. Saint
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16020:10"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, If I ſhall ſpeake with the tongues of men and Angels, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. Which words have given much occaſion of diſpute about this matter. However the words in themſelves are interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as ſpoken hyperbolically, or by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, that is ſuppoſing the Angels had tongues. But in this point Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſeemeth to have gone as farre as ſobriety may ſafely venture, and I conclude with him: <hi>Illud immobiliter tenendum eſſe nullo modo in ſilentio agi militiae coeleſtis officia, &amp;c.</hi> This is to bee holden, without doubt, from the forenamed places of Scripture. That the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the Heavenly Hoaſt are not performed in ſilence, and that the Angels have their maner of tongues, though farre different from all humane. Now, as for their maner of ſpirituall ſpeech, or expreſſion of their Angelical thoughts one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thats the difficulty. And I hope there is none heere that will deſire any ſatisfaction in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo ſublime ſpeculation. As for my owne part, I thinke that moſt true which Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> pronounceth concerning this doubt: <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſciri, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> affirmari poſſe, quanam ratione Angeli vel ad aurem forinſecus vel in animo intus loquantur ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus, aut aliquando locuti ſunt:</hi> That it cannot be knowne or declared any way, how they ſpeak; eyther outwardly in our eares, or inwardly in our hearts, or amongſt themſelves one with another. <hi>Multa nobis cognoſcenda in coelo reſervavit:</hi> ſayth <hi>Zanchy</hi> very well, God hath reſerved many things to be then known when we come to heaven; and of which ſort is this <hi>Quaere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16020:11"/>
            <p>It may ſuffice for our preſent purpoſe to know that this contention or diſputation, was reall, not imaginary or feigned. And as for what paſt in their diſcourſe, though we know nothing, yet we may well ſuſpect the contention to be very ſharpe on both ſides: <hi>Michael</hi> ſtanding in the cauſe of God, in the fulfilling of his command: and the Divel ſtanding in his owne, the advancement of his malicious deſires. Who, notwithſtanding the badneſſe of his cauſe, yet being defeated of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, muſt needs bee eſpecially enraged, to have a limitation ſet on his power, in a matter that ſo much concerned him to effect; and to be enjoined ſilence in a ſecret, the diſcloſing of which, muſt needs have beene ſo advantagious. Heereupon we may neceſſarily conceive him (as his nature is) to have burſt out into bitter blaſphemies and curſed ſpeaking. And as it is commonly knowne to bee the practiſe of thoſe that be of the weaker ſide, and are put to the worſt, to make up that in opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſlanders, ignominious taunts, and blaſphemous rayling, which his weakeneſſe and impotency could not bring to paſſe againſt ſo potent an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary. And this muſt alſo be very remarkeable, as it ſeemes to bee the ground of the Holy Ghoſts obſervation; who much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mends the Archangel in that he did not, <hi>par pari referre,</hi> returne the like for the like, evill for evill, rayling for rayling, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling for reviling, but rather ſayd mildely, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt wittingly conceales the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and blaſphemous language of the Divel,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16020:11"/> as being not to be imitated by us, and to which we are prone enough of our owne ſelves. And expreſſeth the patient anſwer of <hi>Michael</hi> at large, to remayne upon record for a paterne for all men to follow. And of which in the next place I have undertaken to treat of: to wit, the behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the Archangel in this contention, <hi>Hee durſt not bring a rayling accuſation againſt him, but ſayd, The Lord rebuke thee:</hi> which is my ſecond Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; He durſt not bring a rayling acccuſation.</q>
            <p>In theſe words lie the force and ſubſtance of the Text: And they contayne in them a perfect patterne of Evangelicall modeſty: The which I ſhall commend unto you according as the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which may bee gathered out of the Text have ſet it foorth. And firſt, I ſhall conſider it as ſeated in the ſubject of the Text, in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune <hi>Ille, Hee.</hi> The which that hee may appeare the more eminent, the Holy Ghoſt ſets him foorth with all his titles, and writeth his name at length, <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel: or as the Originall more expreſſively, &amp; emphatically, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with a double Article. A mighty and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Angel, no doubt; yet in the exerciſe of that power, how calme, how patient. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell himſelfe with all his rayling cannot force a bitter ſpeech from him. The accuſer of mankind, the ſcorne of Angels, with all his urging inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, cannot extract from him any other, but <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16020:12"/>
            <p>I cannot better expreſſe this extraordinary ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in him, then by looking how farre the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doth prevayle in our ſelves. With whom it is uſuall in this caſe, in ſtead of ſuffering tearmes of reproach, to vie rayling with rayling, and reviling with reviling, from which wee ſeldome deſiſt till our tart language hath fretted off the skin of our Brothers reputation. How doth a poore word miſplaced oftentimes like a ſtone throwne into the water, multiply it ſelfe into almoſt numberleſſe billowes of contention; and of one word in the ſpeech, become a hundred in the reply. It were well to be imagined what we would doe, if wee had ſomewhat of Saint <hi>Michaels</hi> power, who have ſo little of his patience. Which if wee chance to get at any time, good God, how do we lord it? We are preſently at our <hi>ſenties qui vir ſiem,</hi> you ſhall know what a maner of man I am. And in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and as if we had our power for no other end, but to ſerve our owne turnes in this kinde, wee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it to little other uſe, then to revenge our ſelves upon our weaker brother. In this generall defect, I can but guide you to the example heere ſet before us. <hi>Michael</hi> did not ſo, who being an Archangel, and of greater power then wee (in the words of Saint <hi>Peter) durſt not bring ſo much as a rayling accuſation.</hi> So much for the perſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly conſider in the time, when it was ſhewne, in theſe words, <hi>When contending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sea is calme when no winde blowes upon it, and the rougheſt diſpoſitions are temperate, when not provoked. Contention ſtirreth up
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16020:12"/> wrath, and what will wee not doe when wee are angry? To be angry and not fin, <hi>eſt plus quam hu, manum:</hi> more then mans nature is now ſuppoſed, capable of. Let but a matter of variance happen betwixt us, How quickly are wee moved? Let us but fall out, and then wee tell one another their owne: and that in ſuch reprochfull ſpeeches, as if we meant to right our ſelves by rayling, juſt like yong gameſters who throw away their cudgels, and go to hand blows: we leave our legall way of defence, and fall fowle upon each others perſons: and who commonly ſo violent, as they (who like the Divel in my Text) have the worſt cauſe. <hi>Foole</hi> and <hi>Raca,</hi> as if we paſt neyther for Hell, nor the Councill, may be taken for civill termes, amongſt us at ſuch a time. Then is commonly the time, we bring our rayling accuſation againſt our brother: then <hi>effluet,</hi> all ſhall out. Then whatſoever favour, friendſhip, or familiarity, hath betrayed to our knowledge, makes eſcape into the eare of the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by, to the diſgrace of each other. This and the like, if not worſe, is the effect of our contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But what doth <hi>Michael:</hi> this did not he. He contends, but reviles not; reaſons, but railes not; diſputes, but exclaimes not; yea prevailes againſt his adverſary, yet meddles not with his perſon. And how well were it if our variances and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements could bee debated with the like mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? In the meane time I leave thoſe that are guilty heerein, to conſider, ſince they are not <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaels,</hi> who they muſt needs be? and while they follow not him, whoſe imitators they muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16020:13"/> acknowledge themſelves. I paſſe to the next particular, in which the patience of <hi>Michael</hi> is ſhewne, and that is in regard of the perſon hee contended withall, <hi>The Divell.</hi> If any thing might be likely to move him, it were to be gheſt the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe of his Adverſary might. Let us bee heerein our owne judges, what wee our ſelves would doe in the like caſe: what doe we diſdayne more, then that our inferiour ſhould affront us? Should we ſee a baſe beggar dare to contend with us, in any matter that concernes us, how hardly ſhould we forbeare to ſet upon him with contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious words, and tell him his owne in downe right termes. And yet there is ſome compariſon between him and us, where as there was none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and the Divell. Admit a peaſant ſhould raile on a mighty Prince, would we not admire his patience? or would there not be ſonnes of <hi>Zerviah</hi> enow by, to call him dead dog for his paynes. And certainly, what could bee more unworthy this glorious Saint, then the oppoſition of a damned ſpirit: the power of darkeneſſe ſet againſt the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, the accuſer of the brethren, againſt the Champion of the Church: Hell to vaunt it ſelfe againſt Heaven: and how could <hi>Michael</hi> chuſe but tell him ſo? Thou enemy of Mankinde, thou miniſter of darkeneſſe, thou heyre of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thou vaſſall, thou murderer, thou tempter, thou deſtroyer, who art thou that oppoſeſt thy ſelfe againſt the meſſenger of the living God? And yet <hi>Michael</hi> forbeares. And what ſhall I now adde to perfect the commendations of ſo high deſerts?
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16020:13"/> What can I further adde to illuſtrate the unpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld patience of the Archangel?</p>
            <p>And yet I may ſeeme to have ſayd too much by all I have ſayd hitherto already by that that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: <hi>He Durſt not bring a rayling accuſation.</hi> That he did not was a marvell: but if hee durſt not, no wonder if he did not. And this may ſeeme, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignum Michaele,</hi> unworthy of Michael, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from his worthy example. Feare is little better then patience perforce. But this is as praiſe worthy as the reſt. He durſt not, becauſe he would not,<note place="margin">Eſtius in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Et ideo nollet cum poſſet ne nos faciles eſſemus ad maledicendum cuiquam:</hi> Therefore hee would not when he could, that he might not bee an example to us of doing the like. And Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> more emphatically: <hi>Merebatur quidem diabolus maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, ſed per Archangeli os blaſphemia exire, non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit:</hi> The Divell indeed deſerved malediction, but it became not an Archangel to pronounce it: He deſerved a rayling accuſation, but it ſtood not with the dignity of ſo great a perſon to bring it. Blaſphemy and curſed ſpeaking ought not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſacred lips: <hi>Michael</hi> will regard his own perſon before his revenge, which how juſt ſoever, yet was not he a fit inſtrument to inflict it.</p>
            <p>And now, Beloved, let the ſame minde bee in you which was in him. It concernes us likewiſe to ſtand upon eur reputation. Let us conſider what we are, Chriſtians: an honourable title, and not to bee ſtaynd with blaſphemy. When the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe of our nature would prompt us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill language, <hi>meminerimus nos Chriſtianos eſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16020:14"/> remember wee that wee are Chriſtians: and then ſay, <hi>Merentur quidem impii maledicta, ſed per os Chriſtianorum exire non debent:</hi> Wicked men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve curſing for curſing, but that muſt not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of Chriſtians mouthes. Wee are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ought therefore rather to learne of Chriſt, to be lowly and meeke; Learne of me for I am lowly and meeke;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29.</note> not rendring evill for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, nor rebuke for rebuke, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. Wee are heyres of bleſſing, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 8.9. And therefore bleſſe them that curſe you, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.44. Yea bleſſe, I ſay, and curſe not, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14. Let your patient minde be knowne to all men, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5. Wee are reviled, and yet we bleſſe, ſayth Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12. And all this becauſe wee are Chriſtians: <hi>Memento nominis tui.</hi> I have heard of ſome, that have forgotten it: remember thy name which thou ſo often forgetteſt, tis Chriſtian. Speak but Chriſtian from thy heart, and then revile if thou canſt. <hi>Michael</hi> could have rayled; but ſtay, <hi>Ego ſum Michael:</hi> and then <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>He durſt not bring a rayling accuſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet another reaſon remaynes; why <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> would not curſe. Hee remembers, as hee was now <hi>Michael,</hi> ſo the Divell was once <hi>Lucifer.</hi> And therefore he would not doe it:<note place="margin">Lorinus in Loc.</note> 
               <hi>Ob excellentiam na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae quam agnoſcebat in diabolo:</hi> for the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that nature he acknowledged in the perſon of the Divel. <hi>Quamvis alioqui jure poſſet maledice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> although otherwiſe for his ſinne and defection from God, he could have deſervedly reviled him. The Divel was once an Angel of glorious excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16020:14"/> 
               <hi>at cecidit,</hi> but he fell from that eſtate. Once he was in the height of ſplendour, and had his name from it, The bright morning ſtarre; <hi>at ceci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edit iſta ſtella,</hi> but that ſtar is fallen. As a creature, ſo yet he is excellent, though accurſed as a Divel; he is an Angel ſtill though an evill one.</p>
            <p>And according to this is that of a good Author true, <hi>Maledicere eſt adeo illicitum, ut peccatum ſit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledicere diabolo:</hi> It is ſo farre unlawfull to curſe, that it is a ſin to curſe the Divell. Yea the Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> himſelfe ſaith: When the ungodly curſeth the Divel, he curſeth his owne ſoule, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 21.27. And the reaſon heereof is well rendred by <hi>Lorinus: Quia ſimilis eſt ipſi Diabolo impio, nec dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt hic maledicto niſi propter impietatem, &amp;c.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in regard of ſin, he, that is the ungodly man, is like the Divel, &amp; He deſerveth not to be curſed but for his ſin: &amp; what man is he that ſinneth not? ſo that ſo far as a man judgeth the Divel, ſo far he condemneth himſelfe. And whereas wee curſe him as a cauſe of our ſinne, (as too many doe) and yet nevertheleſſe obey him, we may bee thought to returne the malediction on our ſelves, as being acceſſary to our owne ſinne. Let us not therefore rayle on the Divel, but reſiſt him: let us not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him, but defie him. If wee will curſe him as the author and cauſe of our ſinne, let us not obey him when he tempts us to it.</p>
            <p>And if this muſt bee our demeanour and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour towards the Divel, It may teach us alſo a further leſſon, namely how to deale with our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; that we ought to diſtinguiſh betweene the perſon and the offence, the man and his ſin. The
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16020:15"/> perſon of our brother ſhould bee ſacred with us, and therefore inviolable, however his maners bee wicked and intolerable. And although the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked have deſerved evill at our hands, let us not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile them, as being men, and bearing the ſame ſtampe and image of the Creator. And yet they are more then ſo too, they are Chriſtians, ſo alſo to be forborne. If their ſinnes offend us, thats all we can plead; Well, let him that firſt findes fault, caſt the firſt ſtone. Certaynly in many things we offend all, as ſayth Saint <hi>Iames.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 3.2.</note> And if any man dare be ſo bold as to ſay with the proud Phariſie, I am not as this Publican my brother; I wil ſay with the Publicane, Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</p>
            <p>And therefore as for thoſe whoſe heat will not ſuffer them to let paſſe by injuries done unto them by their ungodly brethren, Let them take heede how they encroach upon Gods right: we may be too violent in our owne cauſe, and many times meet with an Adverſary that may bee too potent for us. And the ſafeſt way in this caſe is, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our cauſe to God, who is able, and to whom properly it belongeth to wreake our injuries, and require them at the hands of the wicked that riſe up againſt us.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Samuel.</hi> 24.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> will ſay, The Lord Iudg be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene me and thee, and the Lord avenge me &amp;c. let us refer our cauſe to God. And as hee did in the like caſe, being ſlanderouſly intreated of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. So let us caſt our burden upon the Lord: It is the laſt particular obſervable in <hi>Michaels</hi> behaviour, <hi>Hee durſt not bring a rayling accuſation, but ſayd,</hi>
               <q rend="inline">The Lord rebuke thee.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16020:15"/>
            <p>The Archangel, though a mighty one, as his name imports: the power of God: yet when hee would rebuke the Divell, he calls to mind then, he was a Servant, and ſo it was not in his commiſſion: and though one of his names gave him power to do his office, yet the other might put him in mind of his ſervice: Though he were an Archangel, yet but a miniſtring ſpirit, a delegate, or at moſt a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptayne of thoſe that were in the ſame Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him. And being ſo, it was his office only to bury <hi>Moſes.</hi> If any ſhould reſiſt him in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, the matter was to be referd to the higher power: the ſervants injury is the maſters to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, not his owne; ſo he accounts it. Hee durſt not bring a rayling accuſation himſelfe, but ſayd, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Application is pregnant. As it will not be for our honour, who take upon us the title of Chriſtians, to revile: ſo will it not bee for Gods honour, that we ſhould take the ſword out of his hands. Though we are Chriſtians, yet remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we that we are but ſervants: and if any ſhall diſturbe us in his ſervice, tis our Maſters injury as well as our owne; yea and his onely, as much as belongs to revenge. Vengeance is mine, ſaith the Lord, yea mine, and I will repay it. In the mean time, let our armes be our patience; our ſhield our ſuffering; our guard our ſilence. Let the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked curſe, it is their nature: let us hold our peace, tis our grace. If <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> rayle, it is the King: yea the King of Heaven that commands, anſwer him not a word. If <hi>Shemei</hi> curſe it is <hi>David,</hi> yea
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16020:16"/> it is the God of <hi>David,</hi> that ſaith, Let him alone, and let him curſe, I will requite thee good for his curſing, if not this, yet another day. In the meane ſpace, if our tongues muſt needs bee ſpeaking, let them be bleſſing: if we muſt needs bee anſwering, let us be praying: if we needs muſt bee revenging, let us be reconciling. Let us love our enemies, let us bleſſe them that curſe us, let us pray for them that deſpitefully uſe us: ſo ſhall we be children of our Father which is in Heaven, and conſequently heyres of that Kingdome which he hath prepared for us; and not only for us, but for all thoſe that in patience and well doing expect his appearing; when our Savior ſhall ſay unto us, <hi>Come ye bleſſed children of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to God our heavenly Father, to Chriſt our mercifull Redeemer, to the holy Ghoſt our ever bleſſed Comforter, bee all prayſe, power, might, majeſty and dominion, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 8. 1639.</date>
               <signed>THO. WYKES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 2. line 10. Read, might be in ſome. 7. 20. Dominions. Ibid. in marg. c. 9. §. 10. 20. And that dying. 14. 7. Impoſture. 17. 15. Angelicall.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
